Guide to the Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers 1647-1917 (bulk 1840-1917) MS 605
New-York Historical Society
Guide to the Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers
1647-1917 (bulk 1840-1917)
New-York Historical Society
MS 605
13 Linear feet (28 Boxes, 6 Volumes)
The Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers is one of four discrete but closely related collections, known together as the Alexander - Stuyvesant - Rutherfurd Collections. The Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers contain correspondence and papers of members of the Stuyvesant and Rutherfurd families of New York City and New Jersey. Most of the collection consists of correspondence among members of the immediate family of Lewis Morris Rutherfurd (1816-1892), and his son, Rutherfurd Stuyvesant (1840-1909). Other persons represented in the collection include Lewis Morris Rutherfurd's aunt, Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant (1790-1873), her husband, Peter Gerard Stuyvesant (1778-1847), and her father-in-law, Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant (1727-1805). One series contains material concerning the Stuyvesant Institute, an educational facility in New York City. The collection also contains a small amount of material pertaining to or created by members of the Alexander family of New York City and New Jersey.
Provenance
Donation, Guy G. Rutherfurd, Hugo Rutherfurd, John P. Rutherfurd, Winthrop Rutherfurd, Jan. 1977
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
Biographical Note for the Alexander - Stuyvesant - Rutherfurd Collections
Missing Title
1691 James Alexander born in Scotland, May 27
1693 Mary Spratt born in New York, April 17
1711 Mary Spratt marries Samuel Provoost, October 15
1715 James Alexander arrives in New York
[1719] Samuel Provoost dies
1721 Mary Spratt Provoost marries James Alexander, June 5
1721 Mary Alexander II born
1722 Susanna Alexander born
1726 William Alexander born
1729 Catherine Alexander born
17?? Elizabeth Alexander born
17?? Walter Rutherfurd born in [Edgerston, Roxburghshire] Scotland
1739 Mary Alexander II marries Peter Van Brugh Livingston
1748 William Alexander marries Sarah Livingston
17?? Elizabeth Alexander marries John Stevens
1756 James Alexander dies
1756 Walter Rutherfurd arrives in America. Serves in the Royal American Regiment
1758 Catherine Alexander marries Walter Rutherfurd
1760 Mary Alexander dies, April 18
1760 John Rutherfurd born September 20
1767 Mary Alexander Livingston dies
1782 John Rutherfurd marries Helena Morris October 30. Walter Rutherfurd presents John Rutherfurd with Tranquillity (sic) estate in Allamuchy, Warren County, New Jersey
1783 William Alexander dies, January 15
1788 Robert Walter Rutherfurd born in May
1800 Elizabeth Alexander Stevens dies
1801 Catherine Alexander Rutherfurd dies
1804 Walter Rutherfurd dies January 10
1807 Gen. John Reid dies February 6, at the age of 86
1808 John Rutherfurd moves to Edgerston on the Passaic River
1809 Robert Walter Rutherfurd marries Sabina Morris
1809 Helena Rutherfurd marries Peter Gerard Stuyvesant
1816 Lewis Morris Rutherfurd born November 25 to Robert Walter Rutherfurd and Sabina Morris Rutherfurd
1841 Lewis Morris Rutherfurd marries Margaret Chanler July 22
1842 Stuyvesant Rutherfurd born to Lewis Morris Rutherfurd and Margaret Chanler Rutherfurd
1847 Peter Gerard Stuyvesant dies August 16
[1847] In accordance with a provision of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant's will, Stuyvesant Rutherfurd changes his name to Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
1854 Margaret Rutherfurd born
1859 Louisa Morris Rutherfurd born March 31
ca. 1860 Lewis Morris Rutherfurd Jr. born
1862 Winthrop Rutherfurd born
1863 Rutherfurd Stuyvesant marries Mary Pierrepont
1870 Robert Walter Rutherfurd dies
1873 Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant dies
1879 Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant dies
1879 Margaret Rutherfurd marries Henry White, December 3
1892 Louisa M. Rutherfurd dies
1902 Rutherfurd Stuyvesant marries Countess Matilde E. de Wassanaer (nee Matilde Lowenguth), June 16
1903 Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant born
1906 Alain Stuyvesant born
1907 Stuyvesant Rutherfurd dies July 4
1916 Margaret Rutherfurd White dies
1925 Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant marries Rosalie Pillot
1927 Henry White dies at the age of 77
19?? Lewis Morris Rutherfurd Jr. dies
1944 Winthrop Rutherfurd dies
1944 Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant dies, September 7
1948 Matilde Lowenguth Stuyvesant (in 1948, Princess Alexandre de Caraman Chimay) dies, July 10
1954 Alain Stuyvesant dies, Februrary 9
For more information on some of the persons represented in these collections consult:
Biographical Dictionaries
Dictionary of American Biography- James and William Alexander, Lewis Morris Rutherfurd
American National Biography- James, Mary, and William Alexander, Lewis Morris Rutherfurd, Henry White
Dictionary of National Biography- John Reid
Books
Rutherfurd, Livingston Family Records and Events New York, De Vinne Press, 1894
Valentine, Alan Chester Lord Stirling New York, Oxford University Press, 1969
Scope and Content Notes
Scope and Content for the Alexander - Stuyvesant - Rutherfurd Collections
The Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers is one of four discrete but closely related collections. The largest and the smallest of the four collections, the Alexander Papers and the John Rutherfurd Papers, were originally a single donation, made in the late 19th Century. The remaining two collections, the Rutherfurd Family Papers and the Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers, were donated separately in the 1970's.
Together, these collections chronicle seven generations of an extended family in New York an d New Jersey over the course of two centuries. The founders of the family were James and Mary Alexander, who married in 1721. James Alexander had merchant business, but was primarily active as an attorney and government official in New York and New Jersey. Most of the material in the Alexander Papers derives from James Alexander's legal practice in both colonies, and from his tenures as Surveyor General of New Jersey, and Attorney General of New York. Other material in the Alexander Papers documents Mary Alexander's merchant business in New York, and the business activities and pre-Revolutionary military service of their son, William Alexander (Lord Stirling).
While the daughters of James and Mary Alexander are underrepresented in these collections, their husbands are represented to a greater or lesser extent in each of the collections described below. The Alexanders' four daughters married men who were or would become leading figures in New York and New Jersey. Mary married Peter Van Brugh Livingston, Susanna married John Reid, and Elizabeth married John Stevens. Catherine Alexander married Walter Rutherfurd.
The marriage of Catherine and Walter Rutherfurd also produced a son, John Rutherfurd, who evidently inherited the bulk of his father's and grandfather's papers. In 1847, Stuyvesant Rutherfurd (a grandson John Rutherfurd and nephew of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant), changed his name to Rutherfurd Stuyvesant in accordance with a provision of Peter Gerard Stuyvesant's will. Rutherfurd Stuyvesant evidently inherited at least some of the papers of his uncle. The Rutherfurd collections contain material created by or pertaining to the Alexander family, and the Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers contain material created by or pertaining to the Alexanders and the Stuyvesants.
The material the Rutherfurd collections relates primarily to the landholdings and business undertakings of a wealthy and socially prominent family. The Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers documents the activities of later generations of that family. By the mid-nineteenth century, the family had become more occupied in strictly leisure activities.
Various descendants of John Rutherfurd donated the collections described in these finding aids to the New-York Historical Society, and the collections extensively document the business dealings, professional activities, and family relationships of the Alexanders during the 18th Century, and the Rutherfurds from the 18th until the early 20th centuries.
For finding aids to the other three collections, click on the following links:
The Alexander Papers
The Rutherfurd Family Papers
The John Rutherfurd Papers
Scope and Content for the Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers
This collection contains correspondence and papers of members of the Stuyvesant and Rutherfurd families of New York City and New Jersey. Most of the collection consists of correspondence among members of the immediate family of Lewis Morris Rutherfurd (1816-1892), and his son, Rutherfurd Stuyvesant (1840-1909). Other persons represented in the collection include Lewis Morris Rutherfurd's aunt, Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant (1790-1873), her husband, Peter Gerard Stuyvesant (1778-1847), and her father-in-law, Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant (1727-1805). One series contains material concerning the Stuyvesant Institute, an educational facility in New York City. The collection also contains a small amount of material pertaining to or created by members of the Alexander family of New York City and New Jersey.
The inclusive dates of the collection are 1775 to 1917. The bulk dates of the collection are ca. 1840 to 1917.
Also in the collection is a small group of artifacts, specifically "a piece of wood from the old house" (the specific house unidentified); four metal corners from the cover of an unidentified volume, and a small metal monogram, apparently of Rutherfurd Stuyvesant. In addition, there are numerous photographs. Included are images of items in Rutherfurd Stuyvesant's armor collection, interior and exterior shots of a country estate, probably Tranquillity Farms, and photographs taken during a trip to India, perhapsby Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant and his wife, Rosalie Pillot Stuyvesant.
Whenever possible, series are arranged according to the name of the person to which a given set of material pertains. (For purposes of this arrangement, the names of married women consist of the woman's first name, maiden name, and married name. No middle names are used.) Principal subseries for each person are (if applicable), Letters Received; Accounts, Bills, Receipts (excluding material relating to court cases); Legal Papers (indentures, contracts, deeds, etc.); and Court Papers (material, including accounts bills and receipts, having to do with specific court cases). Other subseries of material specific to each person follow as needed. Material in each subseries is arranged chronologically.
Correspondence is arranged according to recipient, not sender. Thus, there are subseries for each family member entitled [Name] - Letters Received, but no subseries [Name] - Letters Sent. The only exception to this is in those instances where a family member is addressing letters to a group of other persons not specified by name (e.g. "Dear family" or "Dear Children"). In these instances, the subseries is called, for example, Margaret Chanler Rutherfurd -- Letters to her Children.
Six bound volumes are listed at the end of the collection's container list. Two of these volumes are account books of the estate of Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant. Two others, a payroll book and a guest book, relate to the Rutherfurd family's estate, Tranquillity. One other volume is a kennel record of fox terriers bred by Lewis Morris Rutherfurd Jr. and Winthrop Rutherfurd. The final volume is a portfolio of photographs, including both studio portraits and interiors of a residence. Most of the subjects of the portraits are unidentified, and none are identified as members of either the Stuyvesant or Rutherfurd families.
In many instances, correspondence is addressed to a person using a nickname or pet name. Nicknames of members of the Rutherfurd and Stuyvesant families that are used in this collection are: "Loulou", "Poodle", "Ducky" = Louisa Morris Rutherfurd (1859-1892); "Mamie" or "Mamy' = Margaret Pierrepont Stuyvesant; "Daisy" = Margaret Rutherfurd White; "Aunty" = Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant; "Lori" = Rosalie Pillot Stuyvesant.
Very little of the material in the collection was in original order. In instances where material had been kept as a discrete unit by the person to whom it pertains, it was kept together in the arrangement. To use another example for the Rutherfurd Stuyvesant series, there was one cluster of material together in an envelope on which had been written "Papers of the Dino Collection." This envelope contained correspondence regarding Rutherfurd Stuyvesant's purchase of a collection of European armor. Since this material had been kept together, and identified specifically with reference to the purchase of armor, it was not integrated into the subseries Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received. Rather, it was placed in the subseries Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - Armor Collection. Similarly, a group of telegrams from 1903-1904 that appear to have been kept together by Rutherfurd Stuyvesant have been placed in a folder entitled Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - Telegrams Received. Except for this one case, telegrams addressed to a given person were placed in the Letters Received subseries for that person.
Another group of material that had been kept as a discrete unit is the "Stuyvesant Institute Papers." Although these papers were kept as a unit, they do not appear to have been kept in any specific order. Because of the volume of material having to do with the Stuyvesant Institute, it was sorted according to the subseries headings described above (Accounts, Bills, Receipts, Legal Papers and Court Papers, with the subseries title Correspondence replacing Letters Received). This material is arranged as a series (Stuyvesant Institute Papers) of seven folders in Box 13.
Finally, a group of letters received by Sabina Morris Rutherfurd, which appear to have been bound together has been kept in the order in which they were found.
This collection supports research into the social lives of upper class New Yorkers during the 19th and early 20th centuries, detailing their relationships with family and friends, pastimes, travel, and business ventures. The collection contains almost no material regarding the professional activities of the family members. For example, there are only a few letters to Lewis Morris Rutherfurd concerning his work as an astronomer, and there are only two printed articles by him on the subject. The collection contains no notes or drafts of articles by him regarding astronomy.
There is very little material in the collection dealing with political issues. Most such material is correspondence dating from 1849, when a party of family members and family friends is touring Europe. Some of the letters address the political situation, mostly in the context of how it affects the traveling party. Very few letters address the politics of the United States during the period. Some of the letters of Margaret Rutherfurd (Mrs. Henry) White deal with activities at the Court of St. James during the late Victorian era.
Arrangement
The Stuyvesant-Rutherfurd Papers are organized into the following twenty-two series:
Missing Title
Series I: Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
Series II: Mary Pierrepont Stuyvesant
Series III: Peter (Petrus) Stuyvesant
Series IV: Peter Gerard Stuyvesant
Series V: Helena Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
Series VI: Matilde Stuyvesant
Series VII: Nicholas William Stuyvesant [1722-1780]
Series VIII: Alain Stuyvesant
Series IX: Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
Series X: Rosalie Pillot Stuyvesant
Series XI: Mr. and Mrs. Lewis Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
Series XII: Gerardus Stuyvesant
Series XIII: Stuyvesant Family
Series XIV: Stuyvesant Institute
Series XV: Lewis Morris Rutherfurd
Series XVI: Margaret Chanler Rutherfurd
Series XVII: Louisa M. Rutherfurd [1859-1892]
Series XVIII: Margaret Rutherfurd White
Series XIX: Rutherfurd Family
Series XX: Alexander Family
Series XXI: Other Persons
Series XXII: Govert Loockermans--Correspondence and Papers (in Dutch)
Other Series
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The Alexander Papers
The Rutherfurd Family Papers
The John Rutherfurd Papers
Account Books Relating to the Equivalent Lands (BobCat call phrase: BV Alexander)
Alexander, James - Journal 1718 - 1769 (BobCat call phrase: BV Alexander, James)
Alexander, James - Records and Accounts Relating to his Services in Behalf of the Children of Governors Burnet and Hunter, 1718 - 1745 (BobCat call phrase: BV Alexander, James)
Alexander, James - Register of Cases, New York Supreme Court, 1721 - 1742 (BobCat call phrase: BV Alexander, James)
Alexander, William - Ledger, 1766 - 1775 (BobCat call phrase: BV Alexander)
Alexander, William - Account Books, 1756 - 1758, 1763 - 1777 (BobCat call phrase: BV Alexander)
Alexander, William - Battoeman's Book, 1756 (BobCat call phrase: BV Alexander, William - Battoeman)
Alexander, William - Papers Relating to the Disposition of Lord Stirling's lands in Nova Scotia, 1831 - 1838, plus Copies of Earlier Papers (BobCat call phrase: BV Alexander)
Alexander - Livingston - Moore Account Book, ca. 1774 - 1785 (BobCat call phrase: BV Alexander-Livingston-Moore)
William Alexander Papers - Selected Papers in two folio volumes, 1767-1782 (BobCat call phrase: BV Alexander, William)
- Series I Rutherfurd Stuyvesant
  Scope and Contents note
  Series 1 consists of the papers of Rutherfurd Stuyvesant (1842 - 1909). The principal subseries are: Letters Received; Accounts, Bills, Receipts; Legal Papers; and Court Papers. Other subseries (see box and folder list for names) primarily reflect Rutherfurd Stuyvesant's interest in collecting art and armor, and his interest in yachting.
  The series also includes 20 volumes of diaries kept by Rutherfurd Stuyvesant between the years 1869 and 1890. Most of the entries in the diaries are of money paid, received or owed, or of his arrivals and departures on various trips. There are more detailed entries, however, for hunting trips that Rutherfurd Stuyvesant took to the western territories of the United States in 1884 and 1885, and a hunting trip to western Canada in 1888.
  - Subseries 1: Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - Letters Received N.D., 1845-1906; bulk dates: 1865-1906
    Most letters in the series are from members of the Rutherfurd family. For the most part, the letters concern themselves with family and social matters, including the writer's health, news about people that members of the family have visited, and occasionally relations with servants. Intermittently, correspondents make observations about politics. Lewis Morris Rutherfurd writes in November 1865 about the statewide elections in New Jersey ("that last! last! ditch of the rebellion"), and the victory of the Union Party there. A year later, commenting on the congressional elections, he criticizes President Johnson ( "a common street brawler").
    Other correspondents include St. Clare Byrne, naval architect, regarding the design of Arcturus, S. B. Jameson, manager of the family's New Jersey estate, Tranquillity (sic). Rutherfurd Stuyvesant's attorneys, Morris, Sentell & Main, of New York City frequently wrote to him about the state of his business ventures and real estate holdings. Bashford Dean of the Metropolitan Museum of Art corresponded with Rutherfurd Stuyvesant about antique arms and armor.
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, N.D. (1 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, N.D. (2 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, N.D. (3 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1845, 1848, 1860 - 1865 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1867 - 1869 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1870 - 1875 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1876 - [1880] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1880 - 1889 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1890 - 1893 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1894 - July 1895 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, Aug. 1895 - Dec. 1895 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, Jan. 1896 - Aug. 1896 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, Sept. 1896 - Dec. 1896 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, Jan. 1897 - Feb. 1897 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, March 1897 - April 1897 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, May 1897 - June 1897 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, July 1897 - Dec. 1897 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1898 - 1899 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, Feb. 1900 - July 1900 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, Aug. 1900 - Dec. 1900 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, Jan. 1901 - March 1901 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, April 1901 - May 1901 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, June 1901 - Dec. 1901 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1903 - May 1904 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, June 1904 - Dec. 1904 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1905 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, 1906 - Feb. 1907 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Letters Received, March 1907 - Dec. 1907 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - [Rutherfurd Stuyvesant] -- Letters Received, N.D., 1904, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Postcards Received, 1905, [1906] (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Telegrams Received, 1903 - 1904 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2: Rutherfurd Stuyvesant - Accounts, Bills, Receipts N.D., 1865-1907
    There is no material in this subseries dated prior to 1865. Most of the items dated 1866-1867 are from hotels and businesses in Europe, including some receipts for the purchase of art. Much of the material consists of bills for household items such as coal or ice, and receipts for building supplies. Some of the building supplies appear to have been used on rental properties. Approximately half of the material in this subseries dates from the period 1895-1905, and consists of accounts from the Tranquillity Farms estate, or accounts concerning Rutherfurd Stuyvesant's rental properties in New York City.
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, N.D., 1865, 1866 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1867 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1868 - 1869 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1870, 1874, 1877 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1883 - 1893 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1894 - July 1895 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, Novenber - Dec. 1895 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1897 - 1899 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, Jan. 1900 - July 1900 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, Aug. 1900 - 1902 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, 1903 - 1905 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, Jan. 1906 - April 1906 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Accounts, Bills, Receipts, May 1906 - 1907 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Rutherfurd Stuyvesant -- Check Books, 1892 - 1901 (Box 7, Folder 7)